Guide to the Athletic Council Records, 1907 - 1993
Duke University. University Archives
Athletic Council records 1907 - 1993
Duke University. Athletic Council.
11 linear feet Extent: 9500 Items
Duke University. University Archives
The Duke University Athletic Council began in 1907 as the Trinity College Athletic Council. Since that time, it has offered advice and recommendations on the administration of athletics at Duke. The collection includes correspondence, reports, memoranda, minutes, athletic contracts, schedules, statistics, handbooks, newsletters, financial information, and other materials. Major topics include athletics at Duke University, especially football and basketball; Duke's relationship to intercollegiate athletics associations like the ACC (Atlantic Coast Conference), NCAA (National Collegiate Athletics Association), AIAW (Association for Intercollegiate Athletics for Women), and CFA (College Football Association); the financing of college athletics; the management of college athletics; college athletes; and Title IX. English.
UA.13.03.0001
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Records of the University's Board of Trustees which have been in existence for at least fifty years are available for scholarly research with the permission of the University Archivist. Access to records which have been in existence for less than fifty years shall be granted only by special permission, in writing, from the Board of Trustees.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Unprocessed materials are closed pending processing.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Athletic Council Records was received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1975 (A75-45), 1979 (A79-11, A79-112), 1982 (A82-65), 1989 (A89-12), 1992 (A92-98, A92-110), 1993 (A93-123), and 1995 (A95-121).
Historical Note
The Duke University Athletic Council began as the Trinity College Athletic Council in 1907. The Council was reorganized in 1949, 1971, and 1983. Its duties are to serve as an advisory body to the athletics department. Among its duties, the Athletic Council ensures compliance with NCAA and ACC regulations; reviews the budget and advises the Athletic Director on expenditures; makes recommendations on coaching and administrative positions within the Athletics Department; recommends appropriate changes to the athletics program; advises the Athletic Director on scheduling and the adoption of new sports; and makes recommendations to the President and administrative and faculty bodies regarding the status of athletics at Duke.
Collection Overview
The collection includes correspondence, reports, memoranda, minutes, athletic contracts, schedules, statistics, handbooks, newsletters, financial information, and other materials related to the Athletic Council. The first series, Trinity College Athletic Council, contains materials related to the earliest form of the organization. The other materials in the collection derive from the later Duke University Athletic Council. The second series, Duke Athletic Council, contains meetings, minutes, and general files of the Duke Athletic Council. The sixth series, Restricted, contains restricted materials such as student information and Board of Trustee materials. The third series, ACC contains material related to intercollegiate athletics in the Atlantic Coast Conference. The fourth series, NCAA contains minutes, convention proceedings, correspondence, reports and other materials related to intercollegiate athletics in the National Collegiate Athletics Association. The sixth series AIAW contains information about intercollegiate athletics for women. The last series, Oversized Material, contains one folder from the Duke Athletic Council Series.
Subject Headings
Atlantic Coast Conference; College athletes; College sports -- Economic aspects -- United States; College sports -- United States -- Management; Duke University. Athletic Council; Duke University. Athletic Dept; Duke University -- Basketball; Duke University -- Football; National Collegiate Athletic Association; Sex discrimination in sports -- United States; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.); Title IX
Description of the Collection
- Trinity College Athletic Council,1907-1928
  The Trinity College Athletic Council predated the Duke University Athletic Council.
  - Constitution of 1907 (Box 1)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1908-1920 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1913-1919 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence about Equipment, 1913-1920 (Box 1)
  - Receipts of Equipment Returned by Players (Box 1)
  - Student Excuses from Gym Class (Box 1)
  - Tickets (Box 1)
  - The Varsity "T": Rules and Regulations (Box 1)
  - Baseball Schedules (Box 1)
  - Basketball
    - Contracts
      - 1916-1917 (Box 1)
      - 1918-1919 (Box 1)
      - 1919-1920 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1916-1917 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1918-1919 (Box 1)
    - Schedule, 1915-1916 (Box 1)
    - Schedules and Expenses, 1916-1917 (Box 1)
    - Schedules and Expenses, 1919-1920 (Box 1)
  - Football, 1916, 1918 (Box 1)
  - Track
    - Contracts, 1913-1920 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1916-1920 (Box 1)
    - Schedules, Participants, 1912-1920 (Box 1)
  - Stadium Committee, 1928 (Box 1)
- Duke Athletic Council, [2.5 Boxes]
  - Correspondence, (1 of 6) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, (2 of 6) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, (3 of 6) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, (4 of 6) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, (5 of 6) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, (6 of 6) (Box 2)
  - General Files, 1971-1978 (1 of 2)
    - 1971-1978 (2 of 2) (Box 2)
    - Jul. 1, 1976-Jun. 30, 1977 (Box 2)
    - Jul. 1, 1977-Jun. 30, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Policy 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1978-1980 (Box 2)
    - Jul. 1, 1978-Jun. 30, 1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980 (Box 2)
    - 1979-1980 (1 of 2) (Box 2)
    - 1979-1980 (2 of 2) (Box 2)
    - Jul. 1, 1979-Jun. 30, 1980 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - Jul. 1, 1980-Jun. 30, 1981 (Box 2)
    - 1981 (Box 2)
    - Jul. 1, 1981-Jun. 30, 1982 (Box 2)
    - 1982 (1 of 2) (Box 2)
    - 1982 (2 of 2) (Box 2)
    - 1983 (1 of 2) (Box 2)
    - 1983 (2 of 2) (Box 2)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - 1984 (1 of 2) (Box 2)
    - 1984 (2 of 2) (Box 2)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 2)
    - 1985-1986 (1 of 2) (Box 2)
    - 1985-1986 (2 of 2) (Box 2)
  - Meetings, Dec. 3, 1970 (Box 3)
    - 1972 (Box 3)
    - 1973 (Box 3)
    - 1974 (Box 3)
    - 1975 (1 of 2) (Box 3)
    - 1975 (2 of 2) (Box 3)
    - 1976 (1 of 2) (Box 3)
    - 1976 (2 of 2) (Box 3)
    - 1977 (Box 3)
    - 1978 (Box 3)
    - 1979 (Box 3)
    - 1980 (Box 3)
    - 1981 (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1929-1966
    - 1949-1971 (Box 3)
    - 1972-1985 (Box 3)
    - 1973-1979 (Box 3)
  - General Files
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Women's Athletics, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Criteria for Varsity Award, 1983 (Box 3)
    - DUAA Policy, 1976-1977 (Box 3)
    - Taussig, Edward II - Transfer Exception, Aug. 1978 (Box 3)
    - S.S. "Red" Wilson (Box 3)
    - Kornberg Study (Box 3)
    - Subcommittee on Title IX - General Information (1 of 2) (Box 3)
    - Subcommittee on Title IX - General Information (2 of 2) (Box 3)
    - Subcommittee on Title IX - Intercollegiate Athletics Final Report (Box 3)
    - Subcommittee on Title IX - Minutes of Meetings (Box 3)
    - Athletic Report of Ad Hoc Committee of the Academic Council - 1969 (Box 3)
    - Athletic Policy Manual, 1987, 1993 (Box 4)
    - Athletics Committee, Mar. 1979 (Box 4)
    - Responsibilities of Athletics Council, 1984 (Box 4)
    - Intercollegiate Status for Club Sports - Recommendations of the Athletic Council (Box 4)
    - Intercollegiate Stats for Club Sports, 1977-1982 (Box 4)
    - Clippings (1 of 2) (Box 4)
    - Clippings (2 of 2) (Box 4)
    - Mr. Butters (Box 4)
    - Butters Report (Box 4)
    - Graduation Rate Surveys (Box 4)
    - Club Sports Proposal, 1983-1984 (Box 4)
    - DUAA - Women's Softball Application (Box 4)
    - Duke Academic Council Minutes - Athletics, 1971-1973 (Box 4)
    - Athletics and P.E. Committee, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Class Days Missed by Varsity Athletes, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
    - Maximum Awards Legislation, 1985-1986 (Box 4)
    - Pye/Cauitt Letters Re: Industrial National Classic (Box 4)
    - Duke University Dept. of Athletics: Self Evaluation, Feb. 1, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Technical Violation, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Duke/Virginia Tech, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Women's Crew, 1980-1981 (Box 4)
    - Eligibility and Hardship Forms, 1984 (Box 4)
    - Eligibility: East Carolina, 1980 (Box 4)
    - Football Report for Chancellor, May 5, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Form for Fifth Year of Competition at Duke (Box 4)
    - Head Football Coach Selection Criteria: Pye Letter on Recruiting (Box 4)
    - ICTA Women, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Iron Dukes (Box 4)
    - Graduation Rate Survey, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Operating Budgets, DUAA - Professor Edwin Cady, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
    - Policy on "Redshirting" (Box 4)
    - Provost's Task Force on P.E. and Recreation, Nov. 1974 (Box 4)
    - Pye: AM Council on Education (Box 4)
    - Pye Memo on Women's Athletics, Nov. 22, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Recommendations of the Athletic Council on Intercollegiate Athletics at Duke, 1982 (Box 4)
    - Requirements on New Varsity Sports to Mr. Sanford, Feb. 3, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Reports on Athletics at Duke, 1969-1975 (Box 4)
    - Smith, Harmon 1977 (Box 4)
    - Student Survey Athletics (Box 4)
    - Strengthening Academic Standards in College Athletics: Robert E. Klitgaard, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Subcommittee on Title IX: Minutes (Box 4)
    - Subcommittee on Title IX: Report Appendix II A, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Subcommittee on Title IX: Report Appendix II B, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Subcommittee on Title IX: Report Appendix III, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Swimming, 1978 (Box 4)
    - Women's Lacrosse, 1979-1981 (Box 4)
    - Woodyard, Lorraine (Box 4)
    - College Football Assoc. (1 of 3) (Box 4)
    - College Football Assoc. (2 of 3) (Box 4)
    - College Football ASsoc. (3 of 3) (Box 4)
    - Proposed College Football Assm. from R. James (Box 4)
    - Report on Grant-in-Aid Admission, 1970 (Box 4)
- ACC, (1.5 boxes)
  - Meetings (Box 4)
    - 1970 (Box 4)
    - 1971 (Box 4)
    - 1972 (Box 4)
    - 1973 (Box 4)
    - 1974 (Box 5)
    - 1975 (Box 5)
    - 1976 (Box 5)
    - 1977 (Box 5)
    - 1978 (Box 5)
    - 1979 (Box 5)
    - Faculty Representatives, Dec. 5, 1979 (Box 5)
    - Faculty Representatives, Oct. 26, 1980 (Box 5)
    - Cable T.V., 1979 (Box 5)
    - 1980 (1 of 2) (Box 5)
    - 1980 (2 of 2) (Box 5)
    - 1981 (Box 5)
    - 1982 (1 of 2) (Box 5)
    - 1982 (2 of 2) (Box 5)
    - 1983 (1 of 2) (Box 5)
    - 1983 (2 of 2) (Box 5)
    - 1984 (1 of 3) (Box 5)
    - 1984 (2 of 3) (Box 5)
    - 1984 (3 of 3) (Box 5)
    - 1985 (1 of 2) (Box 5)
    - 1985 (2 of 2) (Box 5)
    - Baseball, 1985 (Box 5)
  - General Files
    - Letter to Pye, Dec. 12, 1980 (Box 5)
    - Active File, 1982-1983 (Box 5)
    - D. Leonard, Women's Basketball (Box 5)
    - North Green Country Club, 1983 (Box 5)
    - CFA Television Committee, 1983-1984 (Box 5)
    - ACC Officials, 1980 (Box 5)
    - Basketball, 1979-1980 (Box 5)
    - Budget, 1979 (Box 5)
    - Crowd Control, 1979 (Box 5)
    - Committees (Box 5)
    - Duke Promotional Material (Box 5)
    - Basketball Tournament 1980-1981 (Box 5)
    - Television Committee (Box 5)
    - Review and Preview, Metrosports, 1981-1982 (Box 5)
    - Half-Time T.V. Program Committee, 1980-1982 (Box 5)
    - Long Range Planning Committee, 1974 (Box 5)
    - NCAA Proposals, 1981 (Box 5)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 5)
    - 1974-1975 (1 of 3) (Box 5)
    - 1974-1975 (2 of 3) (Box 5)
    - 1974-1975 (3 of 3) (Box 5)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 5)
    - Constitution and Bylaws, 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - Television Committee, 1983-1984 (Box 5)
    - Long-Range Planning, 1984 (Box 5)
    - Financial Reports, 1978-1984 (Box 5)
- NCAA, (.75 boxes)
  - Correspondence (Box 6)
    - 1973-1977 (1 of 2) (Box 6)
    - 1973-1977 (2 of 2) (Box 6)
  - General Files
    - Special Forms (Box 6)
    - BEOG Grants, 1977 (Box 6)
    - Division I Football (Box 6)
    - IRS Ruling on Radio/T.V. Income (Box 6)
    - ACT Data (Box 6)
    - Educational Rights and Privacy Act (Box 6)
    - Legislative Amendments, 1980 (Box 6)
    - Mailings, 1980-1981 (Box 6)
    - CEO of NCAA Briefing for Mr. Sanford, Kansas City, Sept. 27-28, 1982 (Box 6)
    - Title IX (Box 6)
    - Memoranda (Box 6)
    - Awards Limitations (Interpretations) (Box 6)
    - Re: Soccer America, 1984-1985 (Box 6)
    - Freshman Eligibility Standards, 1984 (Box 6)
    - Normal Progress Rule (Box 6)
  - Meetings
    - 1973 (Box 6)
    - 1975 (Box 6)
    - 1976 (Box 6)
    - 1977 (Box 6)
    - 1983 (Box 6)
    - Convention Jan. 6-9, 1980 (1 of 2) (Box 6)
    - Convention Jan. 6-9, 1980 (2 of 2) (Box 6)
    - Special Convention, 1981 (Box 6)
    - Convention Jan. 12-14, 1981 (Box 6)
    - Convention 1982 (Box 6)
    - Convention 1983 (Box 6)
  - News
    - 1975 (Box 6)
    - 1976 (Box 6)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 6)
- AIAW, (3 folders)
  - AIAW Handbook/Directory (Box 7)
  - Convention, 1980 (Box 7)
  - NCAA v. AIAW (Box 7)
- Restricted, (.5 boxes)
  - ACC Honor Roll (1 or 2) (Box 3)
  - ACC Honor Roll (2 of 2) (Box 3)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Athletics (1 of 4) (Box 3)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Athletics (2 of 4) (Box 3)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Athletics (3 of 4) (Box 3)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Athletics (4 of 4) (Box 3)
  - Athletic Admissions Report (Box 3)
  - Athletic Council Guidelines (Box 3)
  - Berquist Report, Duke Athletics (Box 3)
  - Board of Trustees (1 of 2) (Box 3)
  - Board of Trustees (2 of 2) (Box 3)
  - Chaim Arlosoroff, 1982-1983 (Box 3)
  - Coach Charles Frangos (Box 3)
  - Kenny Dennard, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Duke Trustee Committee on Athletics (1 of 5) (Box 3)
  - Duke Trustee Committee on Athletics (2 of 5) (Box 3)
  - Duke Trustee Committee on Athletics (3 of 5) (Box 3)
  - Duke Trustee Committee on Athletics (4 of 5) (Box 3)
  - Duke Trustee Committee on Athletics (5 of 5) (Box 3)
  - Freshman Football Scholarship - Cahow, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Jill Ann Gambling - Field Hockey Exchange Student, 1984 (Box 3)
  - 1980 Judicial Board Actions vs. Athletes (Box 3)
- Oversize Materials
  - DUAA Forecast Assumptions, 1977 (Box 8)
Related Material
Department of Athletics Records
Duke University Archives
Office of Sports Information and Promotion Records
Duke University Archives
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) Athletic Association Records
Duke University Archives